尼日利亞  拉各斯
巴洛貢市場
密歇根州  底特律
你好  艾比希拉
Hello, Abishola.
我不想讓你大吃一驚
Now, I don't want to alarm you,
但我有勁爆新聞
but I have alarming news.
什么新聞
What is it?
我的表妹迪佩今天早上
My cousin Dipe called me
打電話和我說她的朋友努戈茲
early this morning to tell me that her friend Ngozi
去巴洛貢市場買新的DVD播放機
was at Balogun Market to buy a new DVD player
因為她的孩子往舊的機子里塞了一片吐司
because her baby jammed it with slices of toast.
她簡直暴怒了
She was furious
因為她《毒梟》剛看到倒數第二集
because she was on the second to last episode of Narcos season two.
那家店就在那個
Anyway, the stall is right next to the man
賣假新秀麗箱包的家伙邊上
that sells knockoff Samsonite cases.
仔細看的話那商標其實是"新李麗"
Now, if you look closely, they actually say "Samso-tite."
但是你要是進去...
But when you go inside...
凱米
Kemi.
你能直接說重點嗎
Can you please get to the point?
你不讓我制造懸念嗎
Will you not allow me to build up the suspense?
不行
No.
好吧  你丈夫要來美國了
Fine. Your husband is coming to America.
什么
What?
一個被堵上的播放機怎么會引出這種事
How you know that from a clogged DVD player?
你要是能讓我說完就好了
Well, if you had let me finish.
迪佩和我說她的朋友努戈茲和她說
Dipe told me that her friend Ngozi told her
她看到塔約  也就是艾比希拉的丈夫
that she saw Tayo-- Abishola's husband--
買了一個四輪的大旅行箱
buying a large suitcase, with four wheels.
天啊
Oluwa mi o.
還看到他買了一件有手套的外套
And he was seen buying a coat with mittens.
我的天啊
Oluwa mi o.
他還買了五磅干魚
He also bought five pounds of dried fish
讓店家包了兩遍
and made the man wrap it twice.
我的天啊
Oluwa mi o.
你在嘟囔什么呢
Why are you olo woo-ing that?
這是通德叔叔最喜歡吃的
That is Uncle Tunde's favorite.
飛過來要18小時
And it's an 18-hour flight.
包上兩遍就不會沾上
Wrapping it twice will keep the fish stench
塔約內褲的臭味了
off of Tayo's underpants.
拜托  你們在玩什么尼日利亞迷案呢  這些線索
Oh, come on, all these Nigerian Murder, She Wrote clues
就告訴你  艾比希拉的丈夫要來底特律了嗎
tell you Abishola's husband's coming to Detroit?
-是的  -是的
- Yes. ‭- Yes.
而且他最近一條臉書狀態是
And on his last Facebook post he wrote,
"我要去底特律了"
"I'm going to Detroit."
我的天啊
Oluwa mi o.
鮑勃心動
第二季  第七集
過了一會兒
八年了  他為什么要現在來底特律
It's been eight years. Why is he coming to Detroit now?
是出差
It is a business trip.
真的嗎  我們剛訂婚
Really? So the minute we get engaged,
佳星國際就突然讓他們的副總裁
WellStar International suddenly sends its VP
跑到美國來
all the way to America?
你怎么知道他在哪里工作
How do you know where he works?
開什么玩笑  我上網把他搜了個遍
Are you crazy? I googled the hell out of him.
還有一個叫塔約·阿德班博的低音放克音樂家
There's also a Tayo Adebambo who's a funk bass player.
謝天謝地你嫁的人不是他
Thank God you weren't married to him,
不然我肯定沒有機會
I wouldn't have stood a chance.
他可能會想見見德勒
He will probably want to see Dele.
很合理
That makes sense.
這說明他會來家里
Which means he will be at the apartment
吃幾頓晚餐
for several dinners.
你就不能把德勒從窗戶上吊下去
Can't you just dangle Dele out the window
讓他在街上看看就得了嗎
so he can look at him from the street?
鮑勃
Bob.
我真的不想見他
I really don't want to see him.
也許這樣最好
Maybe this is for the best.
他來見見他的兒子
He comes over, sees his son,
你和他提離婚
you ask him for the divorce,
第二天  你給我帶奧盧的剩菜
you bring me Olu's leftovers the next day.
皆大歡喜
It's a win for everybody.
那倒沒錯
That's true.
記住一件事
Just remember one thing.
謝天謝地
Thank God
你嫁給了另一個阿德班博
you married the wrong Adebambo.
很放克吧
‭Funky, right?
另一天
壽司  無聊
Sushi. Boring.
你們的是什么
What do you guys got?
什么辣非洲菜嗎
Something African and spicy?
我的是火腿三明治
I have a ham sandwich.
我有速食午餐
I have a Lunchable.
想換嗎
Want to trade?
這壽司要30元呢
This is $30 worth of sushi.
加上太陽橙汁就成交
Throw in the Capri Sun, you got a deal.
伙計們
Fellas.
-維勒先生  -維勒先生
- Mr. Wheeler. - Ah, Mr. Wheeler.
我問你們一個問題
Hey, let me ask you a question:
你們在尼日利亞離婚一般要多久
how long does it usually take to get a divorce in Nigeria?
你是說離婚文件
Do you mean how long does it take
要多久才能通過嗎
for the paperwork to go through?
-是的  -我不知道
- Yeah. - I have no idea.
我在尼日利亞沒見過離婚
I have never met a divorced Nigerian.
-我也是  -真的嗎
- Me, neither. - Really?
離婚是很罕見的  幾乎就1%的概率
Divorce is very rare, something like one percent.
拜托  不可能吧
Come on, that can't be right.
離婚和美味的壽司
Divorce and good sushi:
尼日利亞幾乎見不到的兩樣東西
two things you can't find in Nigeria.
你呢
Well, what about you?
你說過你父母在你小時候就不說話了
You said your parents haven't spoken since you were a child.
-但是他們依然是夫妻  -他們開心嗎
- But they stayed married. - Are they happy?
這有什么關系嗎
What does that have to do with anything?
他們剛剛慶祝完50周年紀念日
They just celebrated their 50th anniversary.
爸爸在夏威夷  媽媽在哥斯達黎加
Daddy in Hawaii, and Mummy in Costa Rica.
這上面說尼日利亞離婚率是0.2%
Says here the Nigerian divorce rate is 0.2%.
那幾乎等于零了
That's pretty close to zero.
我不管這是不是百萬中挑一
I don't care if it's one in a million.
艾比希拉必須要離婚
Abishola's getting divorced.
其實  她應該是412萬中挑一
Actually, she would be the one in 4,120,000.
你是在腦子里算出來的嗎
Did you do that math in your head?
-是的  -下次不用大聲說出來
- Yes. - Yeah, next time, keep it there.
-聽聽這個  -怎么了
- Here's something. - What?
500人中有一個有會有11個手指或11個腳趾
One in 500 people have either 11 fingers or 11 toes.
跟我說有什么用
How does that help me?
讓你多了解點嘛
It gives you perspective.
至少你不是那些怪胎
At least you're not one of those weirdos.
失陪一下
Excuse me.
他多長了一個奶頭
He has an extra nipple.
別和他說我告訴你了
Please don't tell him I told you.
當晚
裙子真好看
That's a nice dress.
塔約肯定會喜歡的
Tayo will like it.
不是給他準備的
It's not for him.
我只是剛從柜子里收拾了點舊衣服出來
I just grabbed any old thing from the closet.
你的舊衣服上
Well, your old thing
還有百貨的標簽
has a tag from Nordstrom's.
我不希望他過來
I did not want him to come here.
父親總是要見見兒子的
A father must see his son.
你難道更想去漢堡王之家吃嗎
Would you rather they eat at the home of the Whopper?
我的姐姐養出來的你應該懂事的
I know my sister did not raise you like this.
是的  阿姨
No, Auntie.
那就別說這些有的沒的  幫我做薯泥
So stop talking nonsense and prepare the pounded yam.
塔約更喜歡米飯
Tayo prefers rice to yam o.
是嗎
Does he, now?
-德勒  -媽媽
- Dele. - Yes, Mum?
你給前屋通風了嗎
Did you vacuum the front room?
是的  媽媽
Yes, Mum.
并把我的護士執照
And display my nursing certificates
和你的數學獎杯放在你爸爸能看到的地方了嗎
and your mathematics trophy where your father can see them?
-是的  媽媽  -很好
- Yes, Mum. ‭- Good.
他也許是拋棄了我們
He may have abandoned us,
但這不代表我們過得不好
but that does not mean we're not thriving.
你想讓我這么和他說嗎
Do you want me to say that to him?
別傻了  放獎杯不就是為了這個目的嗎
Don't be ridiculous. That's what the trophies are for.
你是一個好兒子
You are a good son,
你父親會為你自豪的
and your father will be proud of you.
我為你自豪
I am proud of you.
謝謝你  媽媽
Thanks, Mom.
你看起來真的很美
You look really nice.
我和以往看起來一樣
I look the same as always.
把你的書都收起來
Put your books away.
過了一會兒
你好  通德叔叔
E kaale, Uncle Tunde.
塔約
Tayo.
我給你帶了點東西  叔叔
I brought you something, Uncle.
-鱈魚干嗎  -我知道你有多愛這個
- Stockfish? - I know how much you love it.
可算不上是愛
I wouldn't say "Love."
你應該可以進來吧
I suppose you can come in.
我的兒子
Ah, my son.
你好  爸爸
E kaabo, Dad.
瞧瞧你
Look at you.
你長成個男子漢了
You are a man now.
艾比希拉  你好美
Abishola, you look beautiful.
這是條舊裙子  我看起來都一樣
This dress is old. I look the same.
歡迎  塔約
Kaabo, Tayo!
晚上好  阿姨
E kaale, Auntie.
快進來  德勒  幫他拿外套
Come, come. Dele, take his coat.
我們做了你的最愛  西非辣椒燉肉飯
We are having your favorite: jollof rice.
艾比希拉求我做的
Abishola begged me to make it.
在城市另一端
這真不錯  對吧
This is nice, huh?
一家人坐在一起看電視
Just sitting around together, watching TV as a family.
-沒錯  -說得對
- It is. - It really is.
爆米花好了
Oh. Popcorn's ready.
我給大家拿碗
I'll go get us all bowls.
太好了
Great.
我們還要在這坐多久
How long do we have to sit here?
等艾比希拉約會結束
As long as Abishola's on her date.
那不是約會
It's not a date.
當然不是  親愛的
Of course it isn't, honey.
任何超過三小時的晚餐都是約會
Any dinner that lasts longer than three hours is a date.
我有過比那更短的一夜情
I've had shorter one-night stands.
別這樣  這對他來說很不容易
Come on, you guys. This is tough for him.
謝謝  克里斯汀娜
Thank you, Christina.
不客氣  我理解你的痛苦
You are welcome. I understand your pain.
我也做過第三者
I've been the other woman.
你在說什么
What are you talking about?
他們和自己家人吃飯
They're at dinner with their family,
你等著對方發信息
you're waiting for them to text,
你用盡全部力氣
it takes everything in your power
阻止自己跑去那  偷偷從窗戶張望
not to rush over there and peer into their windows
看著他們拆圣誕禮物
and watch them unwrap their Christmas presents.
天吶  這怎么聽上去一點不瘋狂
Oh, God, why doesn't that sound crazy to me?
因為我們愿意為愛做任何事  鮑勃
Because we'd do anything for love, Bob.
任何事
Anything.
這不一樣
It's not the same.
艾比希拉知道她在和鮑勃談戀愛
Abishola knows she's in a relationship with Bob.
-我覺得這沒問題  -你是她的小三
- And I think it's cool. - You're her side piece.
或"破鞋"
Or a "Goomah."
意大利人這么說
That's what the Italians call it.
好吧  這不管用  你們走吧
All right, this isn't working. You guys can go.
就是  媽  道格拉斯  你們沒在幫忙
Yeah, Mom, Douglas, you are not helping.
他們不懂我們
They don't get us.
你姐妹布萊昕怎么樣了
How is your sister Blessing?
還瘋瘋癲癲的  她現在成素食主義者了
Still crazy. She's vegan now.
天吶
Oh, no.
這股瘋勁都傳到尼日利亞了
This madness has reached Nigeria?
我會為她祈禱的
I will pray for her.
那你祈禱時
While you are there,
也為德勒祈禱  他支持阿森納
Pray for Dele. He supports Arsenal.
他們只會讓你心碎
They will just break your heart.
我必須得說  阿姨
I must say, Auntie,
你做的飯比艾比希拉媽媽還好吃
you're an even better cook than Abishola's mother.
等我告訴她時  她肯定氣炸了
When I tell her, she will be furious.
你是來這工作嗎
So, you are in town for business? ?
對  我公司派我來當顧問
Yes. My company has sent me to consult
與橋梁管理局大使商議
with the Ambassador Bridge Authority
我們的全新十億美元的內陸項目
for our new billion-dollar mainland project.
沒錯  你父親在尼日利亞非常成功
Yes, your father is very successful in Nigeria.
要是他沒放棄  他也能在這成功
Had he not given up, he would have been successful here.
或許你對這個國家的信心比我更多
Well, perhaps you had more faith in this country than I did.
或許我對你信心更多
Perhaps I had more faith in you.
我幫你收拾盤子吧
Let me help you clear the plates.
我以前從沒見過你進廚房
I've never seen you set foot in the kitchen.
過去八年我變了很多
Well, I've changed a lot over the last eight years.
這就像你看的肥皂劇一樣
This is like one of your soap operas.
奧盧阿姨還是拒絕買洗碗機
So, Auntie Olu still refuses to buy a dishwasher.
她說家里既然有長手的孩子
She says what is the point when we have a child in the house
要洗碗機干嗎
with two hands?
你知道我租到了什么車嗎
You know what kind of rental car they gave me?
什么車
What?
吉普車
A Jeep.
糟了
Oh, no.
那天在墨西哥  是我這輩子
That day in Mexico, it was the most rain
見過最大的雨
I have ever seen in my life.
如果我們的車有頂
It would have been fine
倒也不會這么慘
if we had a car with a roof on it.
而且你還說服了我那天穿白裙子
and you persuaded me to wear my white dress that day.
就算你又生氣又渾身是泥
Even angry are covered in muck,
你依然是阿卡普爾科最美的女人
you were the most beautiful woman in Acapulco.
太過美麗  以至于酒店門童以為我是流浪漢
So beautiful the hotel doorman thought I was homeless.
很高興見到你  艾比希拉  我很想你
it's good to see you, Abishola. I've missed you.
想念別人最好的方式
A good way to keep from missing someone
就是不要拋棄她們  另娶一房
is to not abandon them and take a second wife.
你完全有理由生我的氣
You have every reason to be angry with me.
我知道
I know.
但我不能給你和德勒
But I was unable to give you and Dele
你想要的生活
the lives that you deserved.
所以你離開了我們
So you left us.
我現在回來了
I am back now.
我現在能給你們提供想要的生活
And I can provide for you both.
塔約
Tayo...
我知道你也想我了
I know you missed me, too.
別這樣
Don't do this.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
我不想讓你不舒服
I don't want to make you uncomfortable.
如果你想的話  我可以離開
If you want me to, I will leave.
繼續刷碗吧
Get back to work.
第二天早晨
早上好
Good morning. ?
怎么樣
So, how'd it go?
塔約來了  看了德勒  吃了飯
Tayo came, he saw Dele, he ate food,
回到酒店去了
He went back to his hotel.
很好  如果你打給我就更好了
Great. I mean, it would have been nice if you called.
我給你發短信了
I texted you.
凌晨一點鐘  你說"挺棒的"
At 1:00 a.m. You said "Went well."
你知道"挺棒的"有多少種意思嗎
You know how many ways you can take "went well"?
事情就是這樣
That's how it went.
你向他提出離婚了嗎
So, did you ask him about a divorce?
沒有
No.
現在時機不對
It was not the right time.
時機對過嗎
Is it ever the right time?
我向我妻子提出離婚的時候
I mean, I asked my wife for a divorce
她正在丹尼斯餐廳吃早飯呢
halfway through her Grand Slam breakfast at Denny's.
別逼我  我會解決的
Do not push me. I'll deal with it.
好吧  我打給了我的律師
Okay. Well, I made a call to my lawyer
想知道我們現在的情況  他說我們...
just to see where we stand, and he said that we sh...
我不在乎你律師說什么
I do not care what your lawyer said.
這件事不是他來解決
He's not the one dealing with it.
也不是你
And neither are you.
我只是想未雨綢繆
I'm just trying to be proactive.
別這樣  我來處理我的丈夫
Well, don't. I will handle my husband.
我現在只需要你耐心
What I need from you now is to be patient.
我就是那個小三啊
I am the side piece.
第二天
叔叔
Uncle,
這個辣肉串上的調料真好吃
the seasoning on this suya is good,
但我忘了美國牛肉吃起來
but I'd forgotten how American meat feels like
就像是在嚼錢包
chewing on a wallet.
多加點胡椒就行了
Just throw some more pepper on it.
這樣你就會再一次忘記
You'll forget again. ?
所以我兒子在這種環境下成長
So my son has grown up not knowing
都不知道正兒八經的事物是什么味道
what real food tastes like.
他的成長環境也沒有你
He also grew up without you.
竟然能在這里見到你
Fancy seeing you here.
你好  通德叔叔
Hey, Uncle Tunde.
真是個美妙的巧合啊
What a wonderful coincidence.
我正在和艾比希拉的丈夫吃飯  而你就出現了
I just happen to be having lunch with Abishola's husband, and you show up.
是啊  真是個美妙的巧合
Yes, what a wonderful coincidence.
世界真小啊
Small world.
鮑勃
Bob.
我知道你是誰
I know who you are.
我在領英上查了你
I looked you up on LinkedIn.
底特律還有另一個牙醫叫鮑勃·惠勒
There's another Detroit Bob Wheeler who's a dentist.
是的  我收到了他的郵件
Yeah, I get his mail.
你介意我們聊聊嗎
You mind if we talk for a second?
當然
Of course.
我們都知道現在是什么情況
Uh, look, we both know what's going on here.
是的  你和我的妻子訂婚了
Yes, you are engaged to my wife.
我傾向于認為是你娶了我的未婚妻
Well, I like to think of it as you're married to my fiancée.
在奧盧的肥皂劇中
In Olu's soap opera,
你們會發現你們是兄弟
you would discover you are brothers.
把馥馥糕遞給我
Pass the fufu.
重點是  你離開了她
The point is, you left her.
她是這么跟你說的嗎
Is that what she told you?
有什么我不知道的嗎
Well, am I missing something?
你是一直躲在通德的地下室里嗎
Have you been in Tunde's basement this whole time?
你說得就像是我大半夜悄悄離開一樣
You make it sound like I left in the middle of the night.
我想讓我的家人和我一起回尼日利亞
I wanted my family to come back to Nigeria with me,
但艾比希拉拒絕了
but Abishola refused.
從某種程度上講是她離開了我
In a way, she is the one who left me.
是這樣嗎
Is that true?
某種程度上
In a way.
根本沒有拋棄這回事
There was no abandonment.
我和我兒子一直有聯系
I've been in constant contact with my son the entire time.
好吧  這我也不知道
Okay, I didn't know that either.
你不知道  是因為我家人的事
You did not know this because it is none of your business
不關你的事
what goes on with my family.
不管你是何說法
Whatever your side of the story is,
你離開八年是事實
you've been gone for eight years.
她現在和我在一起
She's with me now.
也會繼續和我在一起
She's moved on.
艾比希拉和我曾經很幸福  那時我們一無所有
Abishola and I were happy once, when we had nothing.
而現在  我有一座大房子
But now I have a large house,
有司機  有員工
driver, staff.
我還為德勒選了一所很棒的私立學校
And I have picked out a wonderful private school for Dele.
我可以給她她想要的一切
I can provide her with everything that she wants.
所以我要帶她回尼日利亞
And that is why I will be taking her back to Nigeria.
該向前看的  是你
It is time for you to move on.
按肥皂劇情節  你現在會憤然離席
In the soap opera, you would storm out now.
當然你也可以掀翻桌子
You could also turn over the table,
但我還沒吃完
but I am still eating.
天氣真好  對吧
Gorgeous day, huh?
是的  非常好
Yes, it is. Very pretty.
你最終還是會發現的
So, you're gonna find out eventually.
我見了塔約
I met Tayo.
-你什么  -你聽到了
- You did what? - You heard me.
我特別囑咐過不要那么做
I specifically asked you not to do that.
你囑咐過
You did.
但你還是背著我這么做
And yet you went behind my back.
你知道他想帶你和德勒回尼日利亞
You know he wants to take you and Dele back to Nigeria.
這有什么好笑的
Why are you smiling about this?
因為我知道你不會回去
Because I know you're not going.
但他是我丈夫
But he's my husband.
這事關鍵不在他
This isn't about him.
也不在我
Or me.
而在于你
This is about you.
你擁有自己一手創造的生活
You have a life you've created.
有一份自己熱愛的工作
You've got a job you love.
手中緊握著自己的命運
You are in charge of your own destiny.
你不會為了做某個有錢人的小妾
You're not gonna give all that up
就放棄這一切  回尼日利亞去
to go back to Nigeria and be some rich guy's second wife.
是大房
First wife.
管它呢
Whatever.
你已不是八年前他離開時的那個女人了
You're not the same woman he left eight years ago.
塔約不清楚這一點
Tayo doesn't know it.
但我清楚
But I do.
所以你把我看透了
So you have me all figured out.
-并沒有  -回答正確
- Not at all. - Good answer.
那必須的
Yes, it was.
另一天
-你好  -你好
- Karo. - Karo.
你好  爸爸
E karo, Dad.
你準備好出發了嗎
Hey, are you ready to go?
是的  我去拿東西
Yes. Let me grab my stuff.
好
Okay.
我們要和公園里的老爺爺們下棋
We are going to play chess with the old men in the park.
是德勒要下棋
Well, Dele's going to play.
我需要他把我輸掉的錢贏回來
I need him to win back the money that I lost.
你能陪他挺好
It's good you are spending time with him.
是啊  我們又成了一家人
Yes. We are a family again.
我們再也不會成為一家人
We will never be a family again.
我已不是八年前你離開時的那個我了
I am not the same person you left eight years ago.
沒關系
That is all right.
我不是問你意見
I am not asking you if it's all right.
而是在告訴你
I am telling you
離婚是你我最好的選擇
I think it is best we get a divorce.
你不懂什么是才最好的
You do not know what is for the best.
我懂
I do.
而且它是我一直以來
And that is what I've been working for
-努力追尋的目標  -塔約
- all this time. - Tayo...
也是我永遠
And that is why I will never,
永遠不會和你離婚的原因
ever give you a divorce.
我的兒子
Okay, my son.
-準備好了  -是的  再見  媽媽
- Are you ready? - ?Yes. Bye, Mom.
我們會回來吃飯
We will be home for dinner.
未完待續